several years ago a cartoon character
was brought to life on the Silver Screen
when Robin Williams was cast
in the role of Popeye
and if you recall that movie I don't
recall the exact words of what he would
say but the refrain that you heard over
and over again would be he would say
I am who I am who I am who I am
Popeye the Sailor Man I am 2-2 now
I remember seeing that movie and being
intrigued by that particular refrain
that repetition with respect to the
assertion of being
not unlike altogether the way in which
God reveals himself to Moses on Mount
Sinai when he's or in the midianite
wilderness when he says I am
who I am
now I understand that philosophy like
any other science
has its own language
its own lingo
and if you're not familiar with the
language of the particular discipline it
can be somewhat disconcerting and even
intimidating for people and again
philosophy seems to be so abstract and
removed from where we live our daily
lives
and yet there is no more important
question
in all of life
then the question
of being
itself
we can hardly make a sentence in the
English language
without using some form
of the verb to be
am or was were and so on
and every time we make simple sentences
I am going to the store
we were in Orlando yesterday
we are falling back on some kind of idea
of being
it's inescapable
And yet when we begin to probe the idea
of being itself
it's somewhat Elusive and mysterious to
us
well in that period between
the pre-socratics that we've already
covered
and the arrival on the philosophical
scene of the Titan of Athens namely
Socrates
there were some philosophers who were
extremely important not only as
precursors for the coming of Socrates
and Plato
but really for the whole history of
theoretical thought
and those two very important
philosophers of the ancient world were
heraclitus
and Parmenides
now these philosophers were very much
concerned with the question of being now
there's a debate indeed a dispute
over which one wrote first
and which one responded to the other
when I was in college I was taught that
heraclitus wrote first and Parmenides
was answering him
but more recent uh
literature would indicate just the
opposite was the case but we don't know
for sure but I'm going to work today on
the assumption that heraclitus was the
first of these two it's really not all
that important in the final analysis
but heraclitus is known principally only
through quotations and allusions to him
and and fragments of his writings that
have survived but he is famous in
popular Philosophy for some of the
things that he said
and one thing he said was everything
that exists
is in a state of flux
everything is in a state of flux
or to put it another way whatever is
is changing
everything is in a state of change and
his illustration or metaphor by which he
described this phenomenon was to speak
about a river
he said the famous statement you cannot
step into the same river twice
and what did he mean by that I mean you
go to the Mississippi River and you put
your toe in the water step back out and
then step back in you've still stepped
into the Mississippi River you've
stepped in it not once but twice
but what heraclitus is saying is between
that first step and the Second Step the
river has changed the current has moved
on
and the changes that have occurred in
that River may be so tiny so
infinitesimal that they are not at all
perceived for example
every drop of water that moves along
that river is making an impact on the
bank of the river
in a very almost well really
imperceptible way a tiny minute bit of
erosion has taken place and the
composition of the water that you first
stepped into Has Changed by the second
time you step into the river and so
that's what he's saying is that that
river is always changing but not only is
the river changing
but you were changing
and if it takes you uh one second to
step the first time and another second
to step the second time the change in
you again may be imperceptible but if
for no other reason you're still one
second older
than you were
the first time you put your foot in the
river
now this is part and parcel of our daily
experience
we know what it means to age I've said
many times that there are three stages
of Life youth middle age and the third
one you look great
you know you're old when your friends
come up to you and say you look great
that's that's a euphemism for boy have
you gotten wrinkled and gray but we all
know
the ravages of time we all know that as
creatures we are subjected to generation
and decay
to change
we grow older we grow fatter we grow
thinner
whatever
we're always changing
and yet
when you look at a person that you
haven't seen in 25 years you think wow
you know how have they changed it seems
so dramatic when you haven't been there
watching it moment to moment and yet at
the same time you can still recognize
that it's the same person that you knew
25 years ago that you are the same
person you were when you were five years
old or four years old yet
you're different
sameness and differentness
these categories Define
all of reality as we experience it in
the world of creatures
so what heraclitus was getting at
was that whatever is
is changing
he's coming up with a category that
becomes very important for future
philosophical thought
in fact let me say that sentence again
I said he comes up with a character with
a category that becomes very important
for later philosophical thought
and it is the category
of becoming
becoming
now let's talk about these categories of
being and becoming for just another
moment
there are other words that philosophers
later philosophers use particularly
Aristotle
for these categories Aristotle talked
about
actuality
and potentiality
potentiality describes that which we
possibly
could become
but have not yet reached
actuality
describes what we
are
so that potentiality is a descriptive
term for becoming
actuality
is a term for being
now what are you
are you a human being
or are you a human becoming that's
that's the question as long as you're
changing
you are still experiencing potential
you are still in a process
you're still moving
you're still changing
you whatever you are you are not
eternally
the same
so how do we deal with this for for
Parmenides he's saying everything
is in a state of flux everything is in a
state of becoming now having said that
and he's known for saying that many
modern philosophers have appealed to
heraclitus as being the father
of contemporary
existentialism now later on in this
course we'll give a little introduction
to existential philosophy I get that
question all the time from people that
say what is existentialism and I say
it's the philosophy of existence and
they say oh
doesn't help a whole lot
but this whole idea
that there are no absolutes there's
nothing stable there's nothing fixed
there's nothing changeless there's
nothing Eternal only the now only the
individual only existence rather than
Essence these are the thoughts of
contemporary existentialists and they
appeal to heraclitus as their father in
the faith as it were
but believe it or not heraclitus was a
monist
heraclitus believed that all reality was
one
yet
in the one there is
eternal
diversity
in the sense that there is an inner
conflict
within Ultimate Reality
that is essential to its very makeup
that there's a dynamic involved
in reality itself
his greatest model for that was fire
which seems to be alive and Powerful but
it is always burning or going out it's
it's it's kind of the ying and the Yang
the uh the tension or the dialectic
within itself
now over against heraclitus
Parmenides
argued with his most famous statement
that many people have heard me lecture
have heard me refer to parmanitis many
times when I say when I was a student of
philosophy and the first time I heard of
Parmenides and the quotation that was
attributed to him I thought was the
silliest thing I'd ever heard in a
philosophy class and made me wonder why
I was even wasting my time engaged in
this Enterprise because the professor
stood up and he said now here's the key
thought of this great philosopher for
amenities
he wrote it on the board
whatever is comma
is
say wow whatever is is and this guy's
famous for saying something like that
what could be more obvious than whatever
is is
but there's no statement in secular
philosophy that has
jerked me back to contemplation more
often
than that one
whatever is
is
what he's saying is a reality to be real
cannot be changing
because that which is changing
never
truly is
you are not
what you are
because since I've started that sentence
you changed
and not even Robin Williams with the
Popeye image can say I am who I am who I
am who I am
Popeye the Sailor Man
what he should say is
I'm potentially Popeye the Sailor Man
I'm becoming Popeye the Sailor Man
because maybe I was popped by the Sailor
Man but I'm not anymore and even when I
was I wasn't because when I was I was
changing
you can't freeze time with creatures who
are constantly undergoing this state of
flux
that's why it is a matter of great
profundity
that the god of sacred scripture
defines himself
as I am
not I am becoming
not I'm changing
but he is
eternally
perfect
in his actuality
to put it another way for God
there is no potential
God Has No Lack or deficiency into which
he must grow
to realize
his full potential
he has pure actuality
and yet as Aristotle would later
discover
if something
were only potential
and potentially everything
it would be actually
nothing
so this can't be Pure potentiality or
there can't be something that is purely
becoming if all you are is change if all
you are is becoming all that means that
what you are is that you are not
you're an illusion you're a fig newton
of somebody's imagination because you
don't have anything that really is
now many of the thinkers following this
debate in Antiquity came to that
conclusion
they said whatever is is changing if
that's true
then everything that undergoes change is
Just an Illusion
it can't really be
now what does that say about flowers and
rocks and hills and rivers the whole
external world of our experience is an
illusion what about you
if you're undergoing change
and if you're in a state of becoming if
all you are is becoming
then you aren't
you aren't anything you're nothing
but common sense says well I may be
changing but it is an eye
an actuality
who really is changing
but where do I find this being
that keeps me from
just being an illusion
well you're not going to find the answer
in Parmenides you're not going to find
an Eric clitus you're going to have to
go back to Mars Hill and you have to
hear the Apostle Paul say in him you
live and move and have your being
that the only thing that keeps me from
being an illusion
is the power of the one who created me
who himself has all being perfectly
within his own identity
but in any case
this is a very profound thing
to be concerned about as we will see
with Plato and Aristotle and really all
future philosophy in the sense the whole
history of philosophy is an attempt to
answer the debate between heraclitus and
Parmenides between being and becoming
between actuality and potentiality
between reality
and illusion
and that's why these men are so very
important
now
another person that I want to look at
very quickly
in anticipation of the coming of
Socrates on the scene
is a man who's famous if for no other
reason
his name starts with z which makes him a
wonderful candidate to be chosen by
those people who make up crossword
puzzles for the newspaper and if they
have a word with a z in it they have
limit limited possibilities to fill in
the grid and so you'll see this fellow's
name appear frequently if you're a
crossword puzzle addict like I am Zeno
the skeptic of antiquity Zeno was
actually a disciple
of
Parmenides
and he wanted to
attack
all forms
of philosophy that declared the reality
of either matter
or
motion
and he used an argument in his little
games that he played that became quite
important to the whole future of Western
thinking and debate
he made famous the argument called
reduxio
add
absurdum
now the way that kind of an argument
works is you listen to your opponent and
your opponent gives his thesis he gives
the point that he's trying to make
and rather than just counter that by
giving opposite Arguments for it the
person whose reasoning in the in the
fashion of Xena would say okay I'm going
to adopt your position
and I'm going to see where that position
takes me if I follow it to its logical
conclusion
and so Xena would do that he'd step into
the shoes of his opponent and then
reason from the opponent's premise
logically and show that that premise if
reasoned out thoroughly would lead to
Absolute absurdity the Apostle Paul does
that frequently for example in the New
Testament when he writes in First
Corinthians 15 to those who are denying
the resurrection he said okay if there
is no resurrection of the Dead what are
the implications of that and he spells
them out and reduces the arguments of
his opponents to foolishness
well Xeno argues against
pluralism because pluralism taught the
infinite divisibility of matter
and he said this is absurd
and he does this with his arguments from
motion and the famous ones include the
race between
Achilles the Greek Olympic athlete
and the Tortoise
that's sort of like the
fabled race between The Tortoise and the
Hare
but in this case since
Achilles is so speedy
being a fair Sportsman he gives a head
start to the tortoise
and so we have the racetrack
and point a is where Achilles begins and
down the way the tortoise begins and so
uh Achilles has to catch the tortoise to
win the race
so for him to catch and win the race he
has to cover the distance between his
starting point and the starting point of
the tortoise
so he races as fast as he can from point
A to point T where the tortoise started
but no matter how fast he runs
time elapses
and during that time that has elapsed
what is the tortoise doing
he's moving
so the tortoise has moved on
so now Achilles is much closer to the
tortoise that when he started and he has
a much smaller distance to make up and
so he races as fast as he can from the
point he now is to the point where the
tortoise is
covers it very briefly but by the time
he gets to where the tortoise was
the tortoise has moved on
and by logical extension reasoning in
this manner Xeno tries to show
that at what point Achilles will catch
the tortoise where
never
and the Tortoise will win the race the
second illustration is
that if you want to go from Chicago
to Orlando
you can't get there
and his reasoning is this before you go
from Chicago to Orlando you first have
to go halfway
that makes sense
and once you reach the halfway point to
get from that point to Orlando you have
to go
halfway
and once you get to that point
in order to get from there to Orlando
first you have to go what half way
now how long does this halfway business
keep up
forever
we'll never get there
see that's why if I want to go from
Chicago to Orlando and I'm a disciple of
Zeno I plan my trip to Miami
so that on the way I could drop in at
Orlando so anyway this business
of matter reality being and becoming
all set the stage
for the crisis that happens in ancient
Greece
that is not resolved
until the appearance of Socrates